真理被黑暗吞噬之前  童年由听觉  嗅觉和视觉主宰
片名:  穿条纹睡衣的男孩
-快走  -快走
- move! - move it!
快!
Move!
上车!
Now!
我到家了
It's me home.
-再见  布鲁诺  -再见  布鲁诺
- Bye, Bruno! - bye, Bruno!
-嘿  小甜心  -妈妈  这是在干什么
- Hello, sweetheart. - mum, what's going on?
-我们在庆祝  -庆祝?
- We're celebrating. - celebrating?
你爸爸得到晋升了
Your father's been given a promotion.
意思是一份更好的工作  我知道晋升的意思
That means a better job.  I know what promotion is.
我们要开个小型聚会来庆祝一下
So we're having a little party to celebrate.
那他还是军人  对吧
He's still going to be a soldier though, isn't he?
是的  我的小羊羔  只是职务更重要了
Yes, my lamb. yes, just a more important one now.
我还有更令人振奋的消息呢
There's some even more exciting news,
爸爸想亲口告诉你们
But I think dad wanted to tell you about that himself.
-搬家?  搬到哪里  -搬到乡下
- Moving? where to? - to the countryside.
那离这儿很远的  卡尔  里奥和马丁怎么办
That's miles away. what about Karl and Leon and Martin?
小甜心  我知道这并不容易
Sweetheart, I know it's hard,
但我们都必须
But we're all having to say goodbye
和朋友暂时分别了
To our friends for the time being.
总之  我们还会交到新朋友  对吧
Anyway, we'll make new ones where we're going. won't we?
肯当然  你会交到很多新朋友的
Of course you are. you'll make lots of new friends.
布鲁诺  你明早走之前
Bruno, you can have your friends around
可以把朋友叫来玩
In the morning before we go.
把它当作一次冒险  就像书上看到的
Think of it as an adventure, like in one of your books.
但这栋房子是最好的
But this is the best house ever.
那可不一定
Well, you never know.
新房子也许会更好
The house we're going to might be even better.
爸爸说那里有个花园
Dad says it's got a garden.
听着  布鲁诺  作为一名军人
Look, the thing is, Bruno, the thing about being a soldier,
生活中没有很多选择  更多的是责任
Is that life is not so much about choice, it's more about duty,
所以如果国家需要你去  你就得去
So if your country needs you to go somewhere, you go.
当然  如果得到家人的支持
Now, of course, going somewhere else is much easier
搬家会更加开心
When you know that your family are so delighted to go with you.
布鲁诺  每次见你都发现你长高了
Bruno! you're getting bigger every time I see you.
娜莎尼  你才一个礼拜没见他
It's only been a week, Nathalie.
大概是我变矮了吧
Well, perhaps it's me that's getting smaller.
你们俩
So, you two,
你们是怎么想的  关于搬去柏林的事?
Well, what do you think of all this? moving out of berlin?
爸爸和妈妈说这是件好事
Well, mummy and daddy say it's a good thing,
那准错不了
So I suppose it must be.
孩子们  要乖乖的   去拿点吃的
Children, be angels, will you? pass some food around.
希特勒万岁!
Heil hitler!
祝贺你
Congratulations.
-他是不是很英俊  -绝对是
- Doesn't he look wonderful? - absolutely.
我真为你骄傲  我的孩子
I'm so proud of you, my boy.
亲爱的  有时想起来想做梦
Oh, dear. I sometimes wonder if this is all down to me,
为小小的你
Making you those costumes for your little plays
做话剧戏服
When you were tiny.
-你那时喜爱盛装出场  -娜莎尼
- You used to adore all that dressing up. - Nathalie...
现在仍让你觉得与众不同么  亲爱的拉尔夫
Does it still make you feel special, Ralf dear?
这身制服和它的含义
The uniform and what it stands for?
母亲  这是次聚会  我们不要破坏气氛
Mother, it's a party. let's not spoil things.
我  破坏气氛?
Me, spoil things?
你应该小心
You should be careful.
如此公然发表意见可能会给你带来麻烦
Airing your views so publicly could land you in trouble.
你是知道的
You know that.
我们得有多长时间不能见你  我的孩子
So, how long are we losing you for, my boy?
-我想是到战争胜利之时  -那不会很久的
- Until the war is won, I would think. - well, not so long then.
布鲁诺
Bruno!
布鲁诺  该说再见了
All right, Bruno. time to say goodbye.
-再见  -再见
- Bye-bye. - bye-bye!
主  入睡时分以至  感谢你的守护
Time has come for me to sleep lord, I thank thee for thy keep
今晚美妙的夜色  教导我要信赖你
Watch this night well over me and teach me, lord, to trust in thee
关爱幼小  生病  贫穷的人们
Care for children, sick and poor
施恩于他们的人  主  你会给予更多祝福
Grant them, lord, thy blessing more
以基督的名义祈祷  同样关爱我的家人
And this I pray in jesus' name care for my family just the same"
阿门
Amen.
孩子们  看  快看  我们的新家
Children, look. look! our new home.
我有些事要处理  一会儿见
I have some business to take care of. I'll see you shortly.
觉得怎么样
Well, what do we think?
别这样  不是很好么
Come on. it's lovely.
你们俩去选房间吧  我去把玛利亚叫来
You two choose your rooms. I'll have Maria come
让她帮你们拿行李
And help you unpack.
你觉得我们的新房子怎么样  玛利亚
What do you think of it, Maria? the new house.
这不该我来说
It's not for me to say.
好好摆设一下才有家的感觉  对吧
But it won't feel like home until we make it feel like home, will it?
他准备好了么
Is he already up?
他是谁
Who was that?
你爸爸的士兵  我猜
One of your father's soldiers, I suppose.
-他看上去很严肃  -他们都很严肃  对吧
- He looked very serious. - well, they are, aren't they?
-我们为什么要小声说话  -我不知道
- Why are we whispering? - I don't know.
-和谁一起玩  -农场上的小孩
- And play with who? - the children over on the farm.
农场?  我没看到过呀  把那个也递过来
Farm? I didn't see a farm. and that one, too.
只有我的房间能看到
You can only see it from my room.
那里有小孩子?
And there are some children there?
-对  有很多  -那太好了
- Yes, quite a few. - that's good.
-那我能和他们一起玩吧  -当然可以
- So, I'll be able to play with them. - I don't see why not.
我要先等等  看看他们怎么样
I'll wait a little bit, just to see what they're like,
-因为他们看上去有点怪  -那些孩子么
- Because they look a bit strange. - the children do?
-对  还有农民  -怎么个怪法
- Well, and the farmers. - what sort of strange?
抱歉
I'm sorry.
是蔬菜
Vegetables.
放那儿
There.
布鲁诺  你的东西都放好了么
Bruno, have you unpacked everything?
我想你该回楼上去把活干完
Because I think you should go back upstairs and finish off.
谢谢您  太太
Thank you, ma'am.
布鲁诺
Bruno.
-我说过了他们很怪  -谁
- I told you they were strange. - who?
那些农民  他们穿着睡衣
The farmers. they wear pyjamas.
布鲁诺  我正找你呢
Bruno, I was just coming to look for you.
谢谢你的帮助  那很管用
Well, thank you for that. that was extremely useful.
-待会儿见  -是  指挥官
- I'll be over to see you later. - of course, Herr Kommandant.
进来
Come in.
坐下  坐下
Sit down, sit down.
你觉得怎么样
Well, what do you think?
天啊
Oh, dear.
我想回家
I want to go home.
这就是家  布鲁诺  家就是家人所在的地方
You are home, Bruno. home is where the family is.
对么
Isn't that right?
布鲁诺   你至少试着适应这里
Bruno, you have to at least give the place a chance.
我向你保证  用不了多久你就
I promise you, it won't be long before you...
为什么农民都穿着睡衣
Why do the farmers wear pyjamas?
我能从窗户看到他们
I can see them from my window.
布鲁诺  事实上  那些人
The thing is, Bruno, those people...
他们根本不算人
Well, you see, they're not really people at all.
布鲁诺  谁告诉你那里是个农场
Bruno, who told you it was a farm?
-是玛利亚吗  -不是
- Was it Maria? - no.
那里就是个农场  对么
It is a farm, isn't it?
是的
Yes.
那里与你的新工作有关么
Is it to do with your new job?
布鲁诺  你只需知道我在这里的工作
All you need to know about my work here, Bruno,
对我们的国家和你都很重要
Is that it's very important to our country and to you.
我们在非常努力的工作
We're working very hard to make this world a better place
为了让你在更好的世界中成长
For you to grow up in.
但你不是个农民  你是个军人
But you're not a farmer. you're a soldier.
布鲁诺  能过来帮我
Bruno, can you come and help me
整理一下厨房么
Finish sorting out in the kitchen?
但我还是可以和那些孩子一起玩  对么
I can still play with them, though? the children.
布鲁诺  看来不行了
I don't think so, Bruno. no.
就像你说的  他们有点怪  有点儿...
Like you say, they're a bit strange. a bit...
他们和你不一样
Well, they're different.
别担心  宝贝  我们会交到新朋友的
Don't worry, my darling. we'll find you some new friends,
但不是农场上的那些人
But they won't be the ones from the farm.
拉尔夫  你向我保证过
Ralf, you promised.
-你说农场离这儿很远  -没错
- you said it was miles away. - it is.
我怎么能知道他能从卧室的窗户看到它
How was I to know he could see it from the bedroom window?
他们中的一员就在我们的厨房
There was one of them in our kitchen.
-布鲁诺小主人  今天过的怎么样  -很烦
- Master Bruno, how are you today? - fed up.
你这两周每天都说同样的话
You said the same thing every day for two whole weeks.
-没错  -你应该到外面去玩
- It's true. - well, you should be out playing.
-和谁  -不知道  格雷特尔怎么样
- Playing with who? - I don't know. Gretel?
-你可以自娱自乐  -我正在努力那么做
- Well, you can make your own fun. - that's what I'm trying to do.
有件事我很肯定
One thing's for sure,
痛苦地坐在这里不会让你更快乐
Sitting around being miserable won't make things any happier.
-布鲁诺  你在干什么  -探险
- Bruno, what are you doing? - exploring!
不  不  不许去后面  我说过那里禁止入内
No! no, not in the back. I told you, it's out of bounds.
-回前面去探险  -但我已经探遍那里了
- Explore at the front. - but I've explored it all.
-那就找点别的事干  -比如什么呢
- Well, find something else to do. - like what?
先回屋  我们想想干些什么
Come back in now, and we'll think of something.
孩子们  今天做了什么
So, children, what are you doing today?
-和昨天一样  -昨天你干什么了
- Same as yesterday. - and what was that?
-和前天一样  -除了去探险
- Same as the day before. - except you went exploring.
-我喜欢探险  -你去哪儿了
- I like exploring. - where did you go?
我想到后花园去看看  但妈妈不让
I wanted to look in the back garden, but mum wouldn't let me.
后花园?
The back garden?
千万别去
Well, god forbid.
想念你的那些朋友了吧
I expect you'll be missing those friends of yours.
我甚至想念学校
I even miss school.
真不敢想象你会这么说
Well, I never thought I'd hear you say that.
总之  你不会想念很久的
Anyway, you won't be missing it for long.
-真的?  -我给你们两个找了个家庭教师
- Really? - I've arranged a tutor for you both.
李斯特先生每周会来两次
A herr Liszt will be visiting twice a week.
我们不去学校?
So we're not going to school?
学校会来这里?
School's coming here?
骑着我弄到的旧自行车来这里
On an old bicycle, I gather.
是一只失去你的小鸟
It's a bird without you
早上好  小家伙  今天早上怎么样
Good morning, little man. and how are you this morning?
-能问你点事么  -问吧
- Can I ask you a favour? - well, you can ask.
这附近有多余的轮胎么
Are there any spare tyres around?
比如卡车上的旧轮胎什么的
An old one from one of the trucks or something?
在这附近我看到的唯一的旧轮胎
Well, the only spare tyre I've seen around here
属于麦博格上尉
Belongs to Lieutenant Meinberg.
-他还在用它么  -是的  他很需要那东西
- Well, is he using it? - yes, he's very attached to it.
别说了  他不懂  他才八岁
Stop it. he doesn't understand. he's only eight.
你才十二岁  别假装你多大似的
You're only 12, so stop pretending you're any older.
那你想要轮胎干什么
What do you want a tyre for, anyway?
我想做个秋千  -秋千?
- I want to make a swing. - a swing?
听起来挺棒的
That does sound exciting.
你!
You!
马上过来
Here, now.
快!
Move!
带这个孩子到后花园的外屋
Take this boy to the outhouse in the back garden.
那儿有很多轮胎  让他挑一个
There are some tyres in there. he will select one.
然后带上他挑的轮胎  明白么
You will carry it where he asks. do you understand?
小家伙  还等什么呢
Well, little man, what are you waiting for?
这个怎么样
How about this one?
我妈妈在哪儿
Where's my mum?
她出去了
She's out.
-她什么时候回来  -很快  我猜
- When is she back? - soon, I expect.
不用担心
But don't worry.
-但我可能会因失血而亡的  -不  你不会
- But I might bleed to death. - no, you won't.
-我需要去医院么  不  这只是个小伤口
- Will I need to go to hospital? - no. it's only a small cut.
别这样  没那么痛
Come on. it's not that bad.
好了  没事了
There, all better.
-你叫什么  -帕维尔
- What's your name? - Pavel.
在你出去玩儿之前
Now, you've got to sit still for a few minutes
你还得在这儿坐几分钟
Before you start walking around on that again.
你会把这事告诉我妈妈么
Will you tell my mum what happened?
我想她会自己发现的
I think she's going to see it for herself.
她大概会带我去看医生的
She'll probably take me to a doctor.
我想不会
I don't think so.
-这伤可能比看起来更糟糕  -不会的
- It could be worse than it looks. - it isn't.
你怎么知道  你又不是医生
How would you know? you're not a doctor.
-我是  -不  你不是
- Yes, I am. - no, you're not.
你是削土豆的
You peel potatoes.
我接受过医生训练
I practised as a doctor.
在我...
Before i...
在我来这里之前
Before I came here.
如果要接受训练  你的医术一定不高
You couldn't have been much good then, if you had to practise.
你长大后想当什么呢
Now, what are you going to be when you grow up?
我知道  一个探险家
I know. an explorer.
你怎么知道的
How do you know that?
在农场上好么
Is it nice on the farm?
布鲁诺  你这是怎么回事
Bruno. Bruno, what happened to you?
我做了个秋千
I made a swing
但我从上面掉了下来还摔伤了膝盖
but I fell off it and cut my knee.
帕维尔把我抱了进来  还为我缠了绷带
But Pavel here, he carried me in and put a bandage on it.
-回你的房间去  -但帕维尔说我得...
- Go to your room. - but Pavel says i...
别顶嘴  回房间去
Don't argue. go to your room.
谢谢你
Thank you.
你这儿有如此的景色  这真不公平
It's not fair, you having this view.
我可不跟你换屋
Well, I'm not swapping.
看来是学校来了
I think school's here.
不  我是说更近代的历史
No, I mean more recent history.
-你对时事新闻感兴趣么  -是的  非常感兴趣
- Are you interested in current affairs? - yes, very.
那你即将知道
So, you'll be aware of the situation
我们伟大的民族所处的局势
In which our great nation presently finds itself.
是  我一有空就去读报  而且父亲的一个士兵
Yes. I read newspapers whenever I can and one of father's men
总能让我了解最新时事
Keeps me up to date on everything that's happening.
很好  还有你布鲁诺  你看报纸么
Good. and you, Bruno. have you been reading newspapers?
-那你看什么读物吗  -书
- Have you been reading anything? - books.
很好  什么类型的书
Good. what sort of books?
主要是冒险类图书
Adventure books, mainly.
你知道  例如穿着银盔亮甲的骑士
You know, knights in shining armour
在探索陌生的土地和物品
Exploring strange lands and stuff,
还有愚蠢的公主们总是碍手碍脚的
And silly princesses always getting in the way.
这就是我来帮忙的原因
Well, this is why I'm here to help.
你现在多大了  布鲁诺  八岁吧
you're how old now, Bruno? eight?
是时候让你忘掉那些科幻书籍了
Time to get your head out of those fiction books
并且开始学习真相
And start learning about fact.
我想该到让你面对真实世界的时候了
Time, I think, to turn your mind to the real world,
我相信这本书会是个完美的开端
And I believe this would be the perfect start.
死吧  死吧!
Die, die!
Die, die.
你好
Hello.
我正在探险
I'm exploring.
-你在干什么  -我们...  我们正在修建一个新棚屋
- What are you doing? - we're... we're building a new hut.
那边很多都是你的朋友么
Have you got lots of friends over there?
一些是  但我们总是打架
A few. but we fight a lot.
所以我坐在这里  可以自己一个人待着
That's why I like being out here. I can be on my own.
-我叫布鲁诺  -我叫沙暮
- I'm Bruno. - Shmuel.
-什么  -我叫沙暮
- sorry? - I'm Shmuel.
那是你的名字?  从没听过这样的名字
That's your name? never heard of anyone called that before.
我也从没听过有人叫布鲁诺
I've never heard of anyone called bruno.
沙暮  谁会叫沙暮啊
But Shmuel. no one's called Shmuel.
我家在那后面
I live in the house, back there.
-你身上有吃的吗  -没有
- Have you got any food on you? - no.
你饿了?
Are you hungry?
你几岁
How old are you?
-8岁  -我也是呢!
- Eight. - me, too!
真不公平  我整天被关在家里自己待着
It's not fair, me being stuck over here on my own,
可你却能整天和朋友们玩游戏
While you're over there, playing with friends all day.
-游戏？  -那号码
- Playing? - well, that number.
-游戏不是要排号吗  -只是我的编号
- Isn't it a part of a game or something? - it's just my number.
大家都有不同的编号
Everyone gets given a different number.
知道了  然后怎么玩?
Right. then what happens?
-我得回去了!  -真的?
- I have to go back now! - really?
对
Yeah.
沙暮  见到你真好
It was nice to meet you, Shmuel.
我也是  布鲁诺
And you, Bruno.
拜
Bye.
妈妈  我的足球不见了
Mum, I can't find my football.
宝贝  去柜厨里找找
Well, it'll be in one of your cupboards, sweet.
没有  我找过了
It isn't. I've looked.
我可以吃条巧克力吗
Can I have a piece of chocolate?
一条  可以
A piece. yes.
布鲁诺
Bruno?
-找地下室了吗  -地下室?
- have you looked in the cellar? - the cellar?
找你的球
For your football.
该死
Damn.
-格雷特尔  我看见你所有的...-我的什么
- Gretel, I've just seen all your... - all my what?
你的洋娃娃  在地下室
All your dolls, down in the cellar.
小女孩才要洋娃娃
Dolls are for little girls.
现在不该只顾着玩傻娃娃
It's not right to play with silly toys
人人都在为咱们国家无私奉献呢
While people are away risking their lives for the fatherland.
-"吾族之命论乃吾之命论"  -是"命运"
- "My people's density is my density." - destiny.
"吾欲与吾族同舟共济  荣辱与共"
"lts struggles and its sorrows, its joys and its miseries are mine.
"吾欲为吾国之复兴鞠躬尽瘁  死而后己"
"i must work and create for the resurrection of my fatherland.
"吾族上下皆荣耀英勇之士"
"the history of my people is great and glorious."
12点了
And it's 12:00.
-抱歉  接着读   -不是该下课了吗
- I'm sorry? - isn't that when we finish?
布鲁诺  什么时候下课老师说了算
The termination of the lesson is for the tutor to decide, Bruno,
学生说了不算  请你继续
Not the pupil. now, will you please continue.
布鲁诺  你跑哪去了
Bruno, there you are.
我要进城办点事  想一起来吗
I'm just going into town for an hour. do you want to come?
荡秋千一定要小心
You be careful on that thing.
谢谢
Thank you.
问你个问题
Can I ask you something?
你们为啥整天都穿睡衣
Why do you people wear pyjamas all day?
-它们不是睡衣  -看起来好像
- They're not pyjamas. - well, those.
没别的穿的  他们把我们衣服拿走了
We have to. they took all our other clothes away.
-谁拿走的  -当兵的
- Who did? - the soldiers.
那些军人  为什么
The soldiers? why?
我不喜欢那些当兵的  你呢
I don't like soldiers. do you?
我非常喜欢  我爸爸就是个军人
I do, quite. my dad's a soldier,
他肯定不会
But not the sort
无缘无故拿走别人衣服
that takes people's clothes away for no reason.
那是哪种呢
What sort, then?
他是当大官儿的
Well, he's the important sort.
我爸爸能让大家都过的好
He's in charge of making everything better for everyone.
-那你爸爸是农民吗  -不  他是修表的
- So is your dad a farmer? - no, he's a watchmaker.
原来修表  现在大多数时间他在修鞋
Or was. most of the time now, he just mends boots.
这些大人脑子真是坏掉了
It's funny how grown-ups can't make their minds up
不知道自己想干什么  就像帕维尔
About what they want to do. it's like Pavel.
你认识他吗  他住那里
Do you know him? lives over there.
他以前是个医生  现在却在削土豆皮
He used to be a doctor, but gave it all up to peel potatoes.
再问你个问题
Can I ask you another question?
你们烟筒里面烧的什么呀
What do you burn in those chimneys?
我有天看见冒烟了  是些干草什么的吗
I saw them going the other day. is it just lots of hay and stuff?
不知道  我们不能到那儿去
I don't know. we're not allowed over there.
妈妈说是些旧衣服
Mama says it's old clothes.
不管是什么  真难闻
Well, whatever it is, it smells horrid.
我真想你带块巧克力来
I wish you'd remembered the chocolate.
不好意思
Yes, I'm sorry.
我想到了  你可以哪天来我家吃饭
I know! Perhaps you can come and have supper with us sometime.
我不能  因为这个
I can't, can i? because of this.
但那是不让动物出去的呀
But that's to stop the animals getting out, isn't it?
动物  不  是不让人出去的
Animals? no, it's to stop people getting out.
你不能出来吗
Are you not allowed out?
-为什么  你做错什么了  -我是犹太人
- Why? what have you done? - I'm a Jew.
我觉得我该走了
I think I should go now.
-你明天还来这么  -我试试看
- Will you be here tomorrow? - I'll try.
-好的  拜拜  -拜
- Goodbye, then! - bye.
宝贝  给你小礼物
Little present, sweetheart.
谢谢  妈妈
Thank you, mummy.
-瞧见布鲁诺没  -外面玩秋千呢吧
- Have you seen Bruno? - outside on his swing, I think.
行  周四正好  我派辆车接你俩
Yes, thursday's perfect. I'll have a car come to collect you both.
爷爷奶奶要来吗
Are grandma and grandpa coming?
你那天闻到那股臭味儿了吗
Hey, did you smell that horrible smell the other day?
-烟囱里飘出来的臭烟味儿  -哪种病
- Coming from the chimneys. - what sort of ill?
我从秋千上掉下来那天
The day I fell off the swing.
-妈妈  你闻到了吗  -爸
- Did you smell it, mum? - father.
妈妈
Mum.
让我跟她说
Let me speak to her.
是的  我能听见她
Yes, she is. I can hear her.
是的  我们也盼着呢  再见
Yes. we look forward to it. goodbye.
-奶奶不来了吗  -是的
- Is grandma not coming? - no.
似乎她身体很不好  不过爷爷要来
She's poorly, apparently, but grandpa's coming.
-你闻到了吗  爸爸  -闻什么
- Did you smell it, dad? - what?
烟囱飘出来的臭味儿  是什么
That horrid smell from the chimneys. what is it?
我想有时他们烧垃圾吧
I think they just burn rubbish there sometimes.
-那儿  -哪儿
- Look. - what?
-噢!  -格雷特尔
- Hey! - Gretel.
那不公平!
Hey, that's not fair!
-格雷特尔  -什么
- Gretel. - what?
不过是个游戏
It's only a game.
拉尔夫  你请的这个家教老师
Ralf, this tutor you brought in,
他教的孩子像格雷特尔和布鲁诺这么大的吗
Does he usually teach children as young as Gretel and Bruno?
我想是吧  怎么啦
I believe so. why?
我们是不是该了解一下他的教学内容
Well, do we know what he's teaching them?
格雷特尔似乎变得有点
Gretel seems to have become so...
他们学的
They're being taught
和现在孩子们学的一样
What all children are being taught at the moment.
他们不能掉队
They mustn't get left behind.
别想了
Come on.
咱们休息吧
Let's get to bed.
"犹太之流诟吾族  诱吾族之敌"
"The jew slandered us and incited our enemies.
"犹太之流以恶书腐吾族"
"The jew corrupted us through bad books.
"其笑吾族文学音律"
"He mocked our literature and our music.
"凡其所到之处 灾害不断"
"Everywhere, his influence was destructive,
"吾国必因其而亡  不远矣"
"The eventual result of which was our nation's collapse,
-"然..."  -什么事  布鲁诺
- "And then..." - yes, Bruno.
我不明白
I don't understand.
为什么一个人就能让一个国家沦亡
A nation's collapse is all down to this one man?
"其"这里指的是"整个犹太民族"
The Jew here means the entire jewish race.
如果单指一个人的话
If it had been just one man,
真应该千刀万剐了他
I'm sure something would've been done about him.
但是犹太人里面也有好人吧
There is such a thing as a nice Jew, though, isn't there?
布鲁诺  你要是遇到了一个好的犹太人
I think, Bruno, if you ever found a nice jew,
那你真是发现新大陆了
You would be the best explorer in the world.
接着读  格雷特尔
Continue, Gretel.
"其野心乃统辖万民"
"The aim of the jew is to become the ruler of humanity.
"欲开天辟地  然万物因之磨难重重"
"The jew is not creative, but destructive.
"其乃文化之敌"
"He is the enemy of culture.
"数千吾族因其贫困潦倒"
"Thousands of germans have been made poor by the Jew."
布鲁诺小主人
Master Bruno.
你在做什么  你不是刚吃过午饭吗
What are you doing? you've just had your lunch, haven't you?
我要出去走走  但我怕饿
I was going for a walk, and I thought I might get peckish.
别弄乱了书包  拿这儿来
But don't make a mess of your satchel. bring it here.
-我帮你整理好  -不要  你别管
- I'll wrap it properly for you. - no. it's none of your business.
布鲁诺  是什么
Bruno, what is it?
你拿书包做什么
What are you doing with your satchel?
李斯特老师给了我几本书  我想坐秋千上读
Herr Liszt gave us some books. I'm going out on the swing to read.
-让我检查一下  -什么
- Let me see. - what?
-书啊  -不行
- The books. - no.
布鲁诺  我只想知道李斯特老师让你看什么书
Bruno, I just want to see what books Herr Liszt has given you.
-我说谎了  -什么
- I told a lie. - what?
我带的是...
I've just got
历险故事书
Adventure books.
乖  去吧
Go on. off you go, then.
玛利亚  晚饭多准备两个人的份
Now, Maria, there's two extra for supper tonight.
我公公要来
The kommandant's father will be here,
我想科勒特上尉也会一起来
And I believe Lieutenant Kotler is joining us.
接着
Here.
怎么啦
What's the matter?
-别扔过来  -为什么
- Don't throw it back. - what? why not?
-很危险  -危险?
- It's dangerous. - dangerous?
不过是个球  来嘛
It's just a ball. come on.
你爱玩吗
Do you not like playing?
-但不爱玩球?  -这里不能玩
- Just not ball games? - not here.
-告诉我数字游戏咋玩的  -我说过  那不是游戏
- Tell me how the number game works. - I told you, it's not a game.
我们都要有编号
We just all have numbers.
沙暮
Shmuel!
布鲁诺!  你干什么去了
Bruno! what are you doing?
球掉那边了  我刚把它拣回来
My ball went over. I was just getting it back.
这味道越烧越臭啦  是不?
They smell even worse when they burn, don't they?
什么意思?
What?
你知道吧...
But, surely you...
埃尔莎  我发过誓要保密的
Elsa, I was sworn to secrecy.
-连自己老婆也不能说？  -是的
- From your own wife. - yes.
我以生命起誓  明白吗
I took an oath upon my life. do you understand?
埃尔莎  你也该和我一样
Elsa, you believe in this, too.
-希望祖国强盛  -不不不  拉尔夫  不是那样
- You want this country to be strong... - no, Ralf, no! no, not that!
你们怎能...
How can you...
-因为我是军人  -你们怎能...
- Because I'm a soldier. - how can you...
-军人为战争而战斗 -那不能算战争!
- Soldiers fight wars. - that isn't war!
那是战争的一部分  关键一环
It's a part of it! it's a vital part of it!
你我以及大家心中的祖国
The fatherland we all desire, all of us, you included,
若我们不那么做  就不可能强盛
Cannot be achieved without work such as this!
-埃尔莎  -离我远点!  别碰我!
- Elsa. Elsa. - get away from me! get away from me!
爷爷来了
Grandpa's here.
-我不敢相信  -爷爷来了
- I don't believe this. - grandpa's here.
我们一会儿过去
We'll be through in a moment.
谁跟你说的这事儿
Who told you about this?
奶奶怎么样
How's grandma?
天气变化她有点着凉了
She's a bit under the weather, I'm afraid.
真遗憾  她等着盼着要见你们呢
It's a shame, she was so much looking forward to seeing you.
-下次吧  等她感觉好点  -一定
- Perhaps next time, if she feels up to it. - absolutely.
儿子你要明白 你妈真是病了
You know, Ralf, your mother really is sick.
这几周来她一直想着来着
She's been talking about this visit for weeks.
也许是被这想法吓出病来
Maybe that's what's made her sick.
你爸爸跟我说你们有个家教老师
So, your father tells me that you've got a tutor.
是的  他不错
Yes. he's nice.
不过他不让我们读历险故事书
But he won't let us read any adventure books.
学的很没意思  全是古文历史
All we do is boring, old history.
我跟你说  小家伙
Let me tell you something, young man.
没有过去的历史  我们今天无法围坐在一起
If it wasn't for history, we wouldn't all be sitting around this table.
你爸爸在这做的工作
The work your father is doing here,
也是在创造历史
History in the making.
我像你这么大时  我最喜欢历史了
When I was your age, history was my favourite subject by miles,
却很不合我爸的心意
Which obviously didn't please my father.
为什么
Why not?
他是一所大学里的文学教授
Well, he was a professor of literature at the university.
真的吗  现在他还教课吗
Really, does he still teach?
-我不是很清楚  -你这都不清楚
- I don't really know. - you don't know?
我们很久没联系了
We're not in touch, my father and i.
他出国有段时间了
He left the country some time ago.
什么时候
Really, when?
4年多了  指挥官
About four years ago, Herr kommandant.
他肯定还很年轻  大概四十出头
But surely he can't be very old. what is he, still in his 40s, late 40s?
他去哪儿了
Where did he go?
科勒特上尉
Lieutenant kotler,
你那文学教授的父亲  去哪儿了
Your father, the professor of literature, where did he go?
我想是瑞士吧  指挥官
I believe it was Switzerland, Herr Kommandant.
他怎能选择离开自己的祖国
How strange that he should choose to leave the fatherland
尤其在祖国最需要他
At the very moment it needed him most.
人人都该尽其所能的时刻
Just when we're all required to play our part in the national revival.
倒酒!
More wine!
他因为什么出国  他有结核之类的病吗
What reason did he give? was he tubercular?
他是去那儿疗养的吗
Did he go there to take the air?
我恐怕真不清楚  指挥官
I'm afraid I really don't know, Herr Kommandant.
你得问他自己
You'd have to ask him.
那相当难吧  是不
Well, that would be rather difficult, wouldn't it?
因为他在瑞士
With him being in Switzerland.
快点!
Come on!
磨磨蹭蹭的老东西
What's the matter with you tonight?
可能就那原因  因为他病了
Yes, perhaps that was it. perhaps he was ill.
不然的话  他就是反对祖国
Unless, of course, he had disagreements.
-我是说  不支持国家政策  -听说过这类人
- I mean, with government policy. - one hears of such men.
他们大多精神不好  或是胆小怕事
Disturbed, most of them, or just plain cowards.
-不管怎样  他们都属于叛徒  -千真万确
- Even so, all of them traitors. - absolutely right.
如果你父亲是这种人的话
Presumably, if that was the case with your father,
你该遵守军人的职则  上报你的长官
You will have informed your superiors, as is your duty.
科勒特上尉
Lieutenant Kotler!
犹太垃圾  蠢猪
You cretin Jew! filth!
拉尔夫
Ralf!
犹太蠢猪!
Jew!
-但是爸爸只是坐着  -你希望他做什么呢
- But dad just sat there. - what did you expect him to do?
犹太人活该
The Jew deserved it.
问你一些农场的事  好吗
Can I ask you something about the farm?
布鲁诺  你不是现在还认为那是个农场吧
Bruno, you don't still think it's a farm, do you?
是个营地  叫做劳作营
It's a camp. what's called a work camp.
显然是给犹太人准备的
For Jews, obviously.
只给犹太人?
Just Jews?
因为他们干活儿最好吗
Because they're the best workers?
傻瓜  他们不是因为干的好才进去的
They're not in there because they're good, silly.
他们什么都干不好
They're no good at anything.
因为他们邪恶才被关在里面
They're in there because they're evil.
-他们是敌人  -敌人?
- They're the enemy. - the enemy?
-我以为和我们打仗的才是...-布鲁诺 他们很邪恶
- But I thought we were fighting... - they're evil, Bruno.
邪恶  危险的害人精
Evil, dangerous vermin.
是他们让我们输掉战争的
They're the reason we lost the great war.
李斯特先生教我们的内容
Haven't you been listening to anything
你什么都没听吗
Herr Liszt has been telling us?
没  基本没有
No. not really.
爸爸应该不可怕吧  他是个好人
Dad's not horrible, is he? He's a good man.
-当然  -但是他管着那个可怕的地方
- Of course, he is. - But he's in charge of a horrible place.
只有对他们才是可怕的  布鲁诺
It's only horrible for them, Bruno.
我们应该为爸爸感到无比骄傲
We should be proud of dad, now more than ever before.
他正在让这个国家重新兴盛
He's making the country great again.
就和你说的一样  他们有些奇怪  有些...
Like you say, they're a bit strange. a bit...
他们和我们不一样
Well, they're different.
他们是敌人  布鲁诺
They're the enemy, Bruno.
邪恶  危险的害人精
Evil, dangerous vermin.
他们不算是人
Well, you see, they're not really people at all.
你在这里干什么
What are you doing here?
他们需要一个手小点的来清洗这些
They wanted someone with tiny fingers to clean all these.
我们不应该成为朋友
We're not supposed to be friends, you and me.
我们照理是敌人  你原来知道吗
We're meant to be enemies. did you know that?
你想吃点吗
Do you want some?
-你的爸爸是个怎样的人  -怎么问他
- What's your dad like? - What's he like?
他是个好人吗
Is he a good man?
你一直认为他是个好人吗
You've never thought he wasn't?
你为他自豪吗
And you're proud of him?
你不为你的爸爸骄傲吗
Aren't you proud of yours?
在营里真的很可怕吗
Is it really horrible in the camp?
你怎么敢在屋里和人说话
How dare you talk to people in the house.
你怎么敢!
How dare you!
你在吃东西吗
Are you eating?
你在偷吃食物吗
Have you been stealing food?
-回答我  -不  先生  他给我的
- Answer me! - No, sir. he gave it to me.
我们是朋友
He's my friend.
什么
What?
小小先生
Little man,
你认识这个犹太人吗
Do you know this Jew?
不  我正巧走进来  看到他在吃
No, I just walked in, and he was helping himself.
我以前从没见过他
I've never seen him before in my life.
你把玻璃杯擦干净
You, finish cleaning the glasses.
我回来的时候再谈谈
When I come back, we'll have a little chat
如何处置偷吃的老鼠  我们走
About what happens to rats who steal. Come away.
新来到营里的会高兴地发现
New arrivals here are happy to discover that life in the camp
营中的生活不仅仅是干活
Is not all work.
还有很多休闲时光
And that there's ample opportunity for leisure also.
在铁炼厂干了一天的活
At the end of their day at the ironmongery
或者工地或鞋厂  工人们能享受
Or the build or boot factory, the workers can enjoy
营中提供的许多休闲娱乐项目
The many forms of pastime that the camp has to offer.
集体运动非常流行
Organised sport is very popular.
没有玩的人也乐于观看
Those that don't play certainly enjoy watching.
在一天工作结束后
At the end of the working day,
中心咖啡吧是最棒的去处
The centrally located cafe is the ideal place
朋友与家人在那里相聚
For friends and families to join
享受美味营养的晚餐
Together for a hearty and nutritious meal.
尤其孩子们对酥饼和蛋糕爱不释手
The children, in particular, enjoy the pastries and cakes on offer.
晚上还时不时有音乐会
In the evenings, the occasional music concerts,
由访问乐团或者天才音乐者举办
Either by visiting orchestras or, indeed, by talented musicians
营里的人们都乐于观看
From within the camp itself, are always well attended.
别的娱乐项目包括图书馆
Other recreations include reading in the library,
陶艺  料理  艺术  园艺  提供给所有人
Pottery, cookery, art and horticulture for adult and child alike.
营里的娱乐项目多
Almost any activity one could wish for
就怕你想不到
Is available within the camp.
很不错
Splendid.
-精彩  了不起  -谢谢
- Bravo. excellent. - Thank you.
再见  小小先生
Goodbye, little man.
沙暮  沙暮
Shmuel! shmuel!
我不明白
I don't understand.
我看了一个关于营里的影片
I saw a film about the camp,
看起来真不错
And it looked so nice.
我不知道我为什么会那么做
I don't know why I did it.
格雷特尔和每个人都那么说
Gretel and everyone were saying all these things,
那个士兵很吓人
And that soldier's so scary.
我来过好几天你都不在
Been coming here for days, but you were never here.
我还以为我们不再是朋友了
I thought maybe we weren't friends any more.
沙暮  我为我的行为道歉
Shmuel, I'm really sorry for what I did.
我们仍是朋友吧
We are still friends, aren't we?
科特这些天到哪去了  我好久没见他了
Where's Kurt these days? I haven't seen him for ages.
-谁是科特  -科勒特中尉
- Who's Kurt? - Lieutenant Kotler.
他被调去前线
He's been moved to the front.
他的青春与热情
It was felt that his youth and enthusiasm
能在那里得到最大发挥
Would be put to better use there.
指挥官  您的电话
Herr Kommandant, telephone.
事实上  格雷特尔  他会调去那里
In actual fact, Gretel, he was sent there
是因为他没有通告上级
Because he failed to inform the authorities
他的父亲对党不忠
Of his father's lack of loyalty to the party.
必须指出  那是他的义务
Which was his duty, I might add.
-是他运气坏  -运气坏?
- Which was his bad luck. - Bad luck?
不走运的是他父亲不忠
Well, bad luck that it was his father who was disloyal,
而不是母亲
And not his mother.
一般认为没有必要通报母亲不忠
One presumably doesn't have to report one's mother.
-什么?  -帕维尔什么时候回来
- What? - When will Pavel be back?
-妈妈  -永远不会回来  傻瓜
- Mum? - Never, stupid.
是父亲的来电  他们遭到轰炸
It's father. They've been bombed.
奶奶死了
Grandmother's dead.
你为我们和那些死去的人
"...The victory which you have obtained for us
所取得的胜利
"And for all who sleep in him,
让生者永远铭记
"Keep us who are still in the body in everlasting fellowship
在世间的等待
"With all that wait for thee on earth,
是为了天国的重逢
"And with all that are around thee in heaven,
为了与神子耶稣的相会
"In union with him who is the resurrection
圣灵与你同生  伴你复活
"And the life, who live and reigneth with thee and the holy ghost,
唯一的神  无尽的世界  阿门（纳粹的标志）
"Ever one god, world without end. Amen."
那个不可以在上面  她不会想要的
He can't have that on there. she wouldn't have wanted it.
他想要
He does.
万能的神  以自身之死...
"Almighty god, who by the death of..."
你有没有去过葬礼
Have you ever been to a funeral?
我来这以后马上祖父母都死了
My grandma and grandpa both died just after we got here,
但是没有葬礼
But there weren't any funerals.
那个从那里走到那里
That one there to there.
他们同时死的吗
They both died at the same time?
怎么死的
What of?
我不知道
I don't know.
爸爸说他们定是来这途中感染得病
Papa said they must have caught something on the way here.
我们一到这里他们就去了医院
They had to go to a hospital as soon as we arrived.
我们再也没有见过他们
We didn't see them again.
这很好玩
This is fun.
我希望我们能玩些更好玩的
Wish we could do something a bit more exciting, though.
-那个从那走到那  -这个吗
- That one there to there. - This one?
-是这个吗  -不  那个
- This one? - No, that one.
-这个走到这吗  -不  走到那里
- This one to here? - No, there!
-走到这里吗  -不
- To here? - No.
-这里吗  -不
- Here? - No.
-我希望你一直在这  -我也想
- I don't want you to go away again. - No. neither do I.
你不可以这样
You can't behave like this!
-你在对我的行为质问吗  -不能再这样
- You're questioning my behaviour? - It can't continue!
我知道  我不能再忍了  拉尔夫
I know. I can't stand this any more, Ralf.
我不能在这  与这有关系
I can't stay here and be a part of this.
你不认为会有问题吗
Don't you think there will be questions?
-问题?  -大家会议论
- Questions? - Well, now, what does it say
我连家都管理不好
About my ability to carry out my work
怎么做好工作
If I cannot control my own family?
-工作?  你叫这工作?  -冷静点  女人
- Work? Is that what you call it? - Pull yourself together, woman.
对  就忽略它  当没看到
Right. Just ignore it. Ignore it.
忽略这个事实  我嫁了个恶魔
Ignore the fact that the man I married is a monster!
就连你的母亲也不会爱你
Even your own mother couldn't love you.
你们在这里快乐吗
Are you happy here?
是的  很快乐
Yes. very.
你呢  格雷特尔
And you, Gretel?
我原来是的  不过现在想家  想朋友
Well, I was, but I do miss home. I miss my friends.
对  当然  你肯定也是  布鲁诺
Yes, I'm sure. And you, too, Bruno.
肯定想你的朋友
You must miss those friends of yours.
不  一点不想了  真的
No. not any more, really.
真正的问题是  如果有机会
I suppose the real question is, if the opportunity arose,
你们会想离开去别处住吗
Would you prefer to live somewhere else?
-回家吗  -不  不是回柏林  还不是时候
- Back home? - No. Not Berlin. Not yet.
去安全的地方  像海德堡罗蒂阿姨的家
Somewhere safe, say aunt Lottie's in Heidelberg, for example.
我们全家  你也一块吗
All of us? you as well?
不  目前恐怕不行
No. That won't be possible just yet, I'm afraid.
我必须留在这里完成工作
I must stay and complete my work here.
目前  你们的母亲觉得
See, at the moment, your mother is finding it...
她认为你们应该去别处生活
She just feels right now you need to spend some time elsewhere.
你们喜欢吗
Would you like that?
布鲁诺  生活
I'm afraid, Bruno, in life,
常让人身不由己
We often have to do things we don't want to do.
重要的事你们母亲觉得这里
The important thing is your mother does not feel
不适合你们
That this is an appropriate place for you
渡过童年生活
To be spending your childhood,
我多想想
And the more I think about it,
她确实说的对
The more I realise she's very probably right.
-但是  爸爸...  -不
- But, Dad... - No!
是时候你们搬走了
It's time for you to move away.
你还好吧
Is everything all right?
我们找不到爸爸
We can't find papa.
他和一些别的人去了别的工地
He went on a different work duty with some of the men,
但没有回来
And they haven't come back.
我也有些坏消息  我要离开了
I've got some bad news, too. I'm going away.
这次离开多久呢
How long for this time?
所以说是坏消息  可能是永远
That's why it's bad. It's forever, I think.
妈妈说这里不适合孩子  真是愚蠢
Mum says this is no place for children, which is just stupid.
-你什么时候走呢  -明天  午饭后
- When do you go? - Tomorrow. after lunch.
那样我以后再也见不到你了吗
So, I won't ever see you again?
你可以见到我  假期如果喜欢可以来柏林
Yes, you will. You can come on holiday to berlin if you like,
等大家都和睦相处的时候
When everybody's getting on with each other again.
我希望能帮你找到你的爸爸
I wish I could've helped you find your dad.
我真的希望能做些弥补
I really want to make up for letting you down like I did.
那样真的能弥补  是吧  帮你找到爸爸
That would have done it, wouldn't it? Helping you find your dad?
肯定很棒  就像一个机密任务
Would've been great. Like a secret mission.
-我可以从下面挖开  -什么  用那个吗
- I could dig under. - What? With that?
不  但我能带工具
No, but I could bring something.
这边可一点都不好玩
You don't want to come over here.
看
Look.
-我能去你那边  -干什么呢
- I could come through to your side. - what's the point in that?
你爸爸肯定不会在我这边  是吧
Your dad's not going to be over here, is he?
但我过来肯定会显眼  是吧
But I'd stick out though, wouldn't I, if I came through?
我和你们不一样
I don't look like you.
可以打扮一下
You could look like me, though.
穿成一样的衣服  剃了头发
If you dressed like me and shaved your hair off.
我不会把头发剃了
I'm not shaving my hair off.
-你可以戴帽子  -我的睡衣颜色不对
- You could cover it with a cap. - My pyjamas are a different colour.
我可以带给你  那里有一房的睡衣
I could bring some. there's a hut full of them,
几千件  你真的愿意吗
Thousands of them. Would you do it, though?
-我想那么做  -你真的敢吗
- I want to do it. - Would you dare do it, though?
-我想帮你找到你爸爸  -我得走了
- I want to help you find your dad. - I've got to go.
那么就明天  我会带超大三明治
Tomorrow, then? I'll bring an extra-big sandwich.
别忘了睡衣
And don't forget the pyjamas!
布鲁诺
Bruno?
妈妈  我能去荡秋千吗
Mum, can I go and play on the swing?
-布鲁诺  -最后一次了
- Bruno... - It's my last chance.
好吧  那去吧
All right. go on then.
我还以为你不来了
I thought you weren't coming!
对不起  不容易脱身
I'm sorry. it wasn't easy to get away.
我今天不容易出门  你忘了睡衣
I'm not meant to be out here today. You forgot the pyjamas!
-三明治带了吗  -我怎么会让你失望
- Did you bring the sandwich? - Would I let you down?
沙暮
Shmuel.
这里
Here.
我看起来如何
How do I look?
好  让我们开始干活
Right. let's get going.
布鲁诺
Bruno?
这点深够了
That's enough.
我们去找你爸爸
Let's go and find your dad.
快点!
Come on!
布鲁诺小主人
Master Bruno?
沙暮
Shmuel.
-能去咖啡吧或者别的地方吗  -咖啡吧?
- Can we go to the cafe or something? - cafe?
-也许我该回家了  -那爸爸呢
- Maybe I should go home. - What about papa?
我们先查下我们的屋子
We'll check our hut first.
布鲁诺
Bruno?
快点
Come on.
爸爸?
Papa?
起来! 起来!
Up! up! get up!
-发生什么事了  -我不知道
- What's happening? - I don't know.
我们有时会走队列
We go on marches sometimes.
走!  起来!
Move! up, up!
走! 走!
Move, move!
布鲁诺
Bruno!
他肯定还在外面  夫人
He must still be outside somewhere, Ma'am.
布鲁诺
Bruno!
Bruno?
-走!  -快点!
- Move! - Quickly!
起来!
Get up!
起来  你必须起来!
Get up. you must!
把他们拖出来!
Move them out!
...那样我们每周的容纳人数
...which means that our weekly capabilities
就会几乎翻三翻
Would be almost tripled,
那样  在夏天结束之前
So, therefore, by the end of the summer...
-拉尔夫  -埃尔莎  我在开会
- Ralf. - Elsa, I'm in a meeting.
布鲁诺不见了
Bruno's missing.
快点!
Come on!
在这里等着!
Wait here!
快点!
Come on!
走!  快走!
Move! move!
到队伍里去!
Join the queue!
快点  你
Come on, you!
布鲁诺
Bruno!
快走
Move it!
继续
Go on.
布鲁诺
Bruno!
没关系  我们就在这里等雨停
It's all right. I think we're just waiting in here until the rain stops.
脱下衣服!
Clothes off!
我们去哪里
Where are we going?
只是个淋浴
No, it's just a shower.
淋浴?
A shower?
开门!  开门!
Open the gates! open the gates!
快走!
Move!
布鲁诺
Bruno!